It has been 128 years
مضى من الزمن ١٢٨ عاماً
since the last country in the world abolished slavery
على إلغاء آخر بلد في العالم لمنهج العبودية
and 53 years
ومضى من الزمن ٥٣ عاماً
since Martin Luther King pronounced his "I Have A Dream" speech.
على تأدية "مارتن لوثر كينغ" خطابه الشهير "لدي حلم".
But we still live in a world
ولكن ما زلنا نعيش في عالم
where the color of our skin not only gives a first impression,
حيث أن لون بشرتنا لا يعطي الانطباع الأول فقط،
but a lasting one that remains.
ولكن انطباعاً يدوم الى الأبد.
I was born in a family full of colors.
ولدت في عائلة متعددة الألوان.
My father is the son of a maid
والدي هو ابن خادمة
from whom he inherited an intense dark chocolate tone.
والذي ورث منها لون البشرة والتي على هيئة الشوكولاتة الداكنة المكثفة.
He was adopted by those who I know as my grandparents.
تم تبنيه من قبل من اعرفهم على انهم جدي وجدتي.
The matriarch, my grandma,
الأم الحاكمة، جدتي،
has a porcelain skin and cotton-like hair.
لديها جلد كالبورسلان وشعر مثل القطن.
My grandpa was somewhere between a vanilla and strawberry yogurt tone,
كان لون بشرة جدي في مكان ما بين الفانيليا والفراولة واللبن الزبادي،
like my uncle and my cousin.
مثل عمي وابن عمي.
My mother is a cinnamon-skin daughter of a native Brazilian,
لون جلد والدتي كلون القرفة وهي ابنة لأم من أصل برازيلي،
with a pinch of hazel and honey,
مع القليل من لون البندق والعسل،
and a man [who is] a mix of coffee with milk,
مع رجل لون بشرته مزيج من القهوة مع الحليب،
but with a lot of coffee.
ولكن مع الكثير من القهوة.
She has two sisters.
لديها شقيقتين.
One in a toasted-peanut skin
لون جلد واحدة منهن كالفول المحمص السوداني
and the other,
والأخرى،
also adopted,
والتي تم تبنيها ايضاً،
more on the beige side,
يميل لون بشرتها أكثر للون البيج،
like a pancake.
مثل الفطيرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Growing up in this family,
ولأنني نشئت في هذه العائلة،
color was never important for me.
لم يكن لون البشرة مهما بالنسبة لي.
Outside home, however, things were different soon.
ولكن اصبحت الأمور مختلفة خارج المنزل.
Color had many other meanings.
اذ كان للون معاني كثيرة أخرى.
I remember my first drawing lessons in school
اذكر اول دروس لي في الرسم في المدرسة
as a bunch of contradictory feelings.
كانت على شكل حفنة من المشاعر المتناقضة.
It was exciting and creative
كان الامر مثيرا وباعثا للأبداع
but I never understood the unique flesh-colored pencil.
لكنني لم أفهم قط القلم الخاص بلون البشرة.
I was made of flesh but I wasn't pink.
اذ انني انسانة ايضاً ولكن لم تكن بشرتي زهرية
My skin was brown, and people said I was black.
بشرتي بنية، ويقال انني سوداء
I was seven years old with a mess of colors in my head.
كنت حينها في السابعة من العمر، مع فوضى من الألوان في رأسي.
Later,
وفي وقت لاحق،
when I took my cousin to school,
عندما أخذت ابن عمي إلى المدرسة،
I was usually taken for the nanny.
كان يتم عادة اصطحابي لمربية الأطفال.
By helping in the kitchen at a friend's party,
وعندما كنت اساعد اصدقائي في المطبخ خلال الحفلات،
people thought I was the maid.
كان يعتقد المدعوون أنني الخادمة.
I was even treated like a prostitute
وعوملت أيضاً على انني بائعة هوى
just because I was walking alone on the beach with European friends.
فقط لأنني كنت امشي وحدي على الشاطئ مع أصدقائي الأوروبيين.
And many times,
وفي كثير من الاحيان،
visiting my grandma or friends in upper class buildings,
وعند زيارة جدتي أو اصدقائي في مباني الطبقة الراقية،
I was invited not to use the main elevator.
يطلب مني عدم استخدام المصعد الرئيسي.
Because in the end,
لأنه وفي النهاية،
with this color and this hair,
لا يمكنني مع هذا اللون من البشرة ولا مع هذا الشعر،
I cannot belong to some places.
أن أنتمي إلى بعض الأماكن.
In some way,
وبطريقة ما،
I get to used to it and accept part of it.
اعتدت على هذا المفهوم وقبلت جزءا منه.
However, something inside of me keeps revolving and struggling.
لكن ومع ذلك، بقي يدور شيء في داخلي ويكافح.
Years later I married a Spaniard.
وبعد سنوات، تزوجت من اسباني.
But not any Spaniard.
ولكن ليس أي اسباني.
I chose one with the skin color of a lobster when sunburnt.
اخترت واحدا مع لون بشرة الكركند شديد الاحمرار.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Since then, a new question started to chase me.
ومنذ ذلك الحين، طاردني سؤال جديد
What will be the color of your children?
ماذا سيكون لون أطفالك؟
As you can understand, this is my last concern.
وكما تعلمون فان ذلك لا يعنيني.
But thinking about it,
ولكن التفكير فيه،
with my previous background,
ومع خلفيتي السابقة،
my story led me to make my personal exercise as a photographer.
قادتني تجربتي الخاصة لأصبح مصورة فوتوغرافية
And that is how Humanae was born.
وهكذا ولدت فكرة "هيوماناي".
Humanae is a pursuit to highlight our true colors,
مضمون "هيوماناي" هو السعي لتسليط الضوء على ألواننا الحقيقية،
rather than the untrue
عوضاً عن ألوان لا تعكس حقيقتنا
white, red, black or yellow associated with race.
مثل الأبيض والأحمر والأسود أو الأصفر والمرتبطة مع العرق.
It's a kind of game to question our codes.
هي عبارة عن لعبة لإعادة النظر في افكارنا ومعتقداتنا.
It's a work in progress from a personal story to a global history.
انه عمل قيد الانجاز نابع من قصة شخصية الى تاريخ عالمي.
I portray the subjects in a white background.
اقوم بتصوير المشاركين على خلفية بيضاء
Then I choose an 11-pixel square from the nose,
ثم اختار مربع بقياس ١١ بكسل من الأنف،
paint the background,
واقوم بطلاء الخلفية،
and look for the corresponding color in the industrial palette, Pantone.
وابحث عن اللون المطابق في لوح الألوان الصناعي، بانتون.
I started with my family and friends,
بدأت أولاً مع عائلتي وأصدقائي،
then more and more people joined the adventure,
ثم انضم المزيد والمزيد من الاشخاص إلى المغامرة،
thanks to public calls coming through the social media.
وذلك بفضل الدعوات العامة من خلال وسائل الاعلام الاجتماعية.
I thought that the main space to show my work was the Internet
واعتقدت أن الفضاء الرئيسي لإظهار عملي كان الإنترنت
because I want an open concept that invites everybody
لأنني أريد مفهوماً بلا قيود يقوم بدعوة الجميع
to push the share button in both the computer and their brain.
للضغط على زر المشاركة في جهاز الكمبيوتر وفي عقولهم.
The snowball started to roll.
بدأت كرة الثلج بالتدحرج.
The project had a great welcome --
وتلقى المشروع ترحيبا كبيرا
invitations, exhibitions,
دعوات ومعارض،
physical formats,
على شكل فنون ملموسة،
galleries and museums ...
صالات العرض والمتاحف
just happened.
حصل كل ذلك بالفعل.
And among them, my favorite:
والامر المفضل لدي والذي هو من بين كل هذه الأمور
when Humanae occupies public spaces
وهو عند احتلال "هيوماناي" الأماكن العامة
and appears in the street,
والظهور في الشوارع،
it fosters a popular debate
اذ يعزز ذلك من مفهوم النقاش العام
and creates a feeling of community.
ويخلق شعورا من الانتماء في المجتمع.
I have portrayed more than 3,000 people
قمت بتصوير أكثر من ٣٠٠٠ شخص
in 13 different countries,
في ١٣ بلدا مختلفا،
19 different cities around the world.
في ١٩ مدينة مختلفة في جميع أنحاء العالم.
Just to mention some of them --
ولإعطائكم لمحة عن بعضهم
from someone included in the Forbes list,
منهم من هم في قائمة مجلة فوربس،
to refugees who crossed the Mediterranean by boat.
ومنهم اللاجئون والذين عبروا البحر الأبيض المتوسط عن طريق القوارب.
In Paris, from the UNESCO Headquarters to a shelter.
وفي باريس، منهم من هم في مقر اليونسكو ومنهم من هم في الملاجئ.
And students both in Switzerland and favelas in Rio de Janeiro.
ومنهم طلاب في سويسرا والأحياء الفقيرة في ريو دي جانيرو على حد سواء.
All kinds of beliefs,
من جميع أنواع المعتقدات،
gender identities
والهويات الجنسية
or physical impairments,
أو العاهات البدنية،
a newborn or terminally ill.
ومنهم الأطفال حديثي الولادة أو المرضى الميؤوس من شفائهم.
We all together build Humanae.
قمنا جميعا ببناء "هيوماني"
Those portraits make us rethink how we see each other.
تحثنا هذه الصور على اعادة التفكير في نموذج رؤيتنا بعضنا البعض.
When modern science is questioning the race concept,
عندما يقوم العلم الحديث بإطلاق البحوث عن مفاهيم ومبادئ العرق،
what does it mean for us to be black, white, yellow, red?
وعن معنى كوننا من ذوي البشرة السوداء أو البيضاء أو الصفراء أو الحمراء؟
Is it the eye, the nose, the mouth, the hair?
هل للأمر علاقة في نمط او شكل العين، أو الأنف، أو الفم، أو الشعر؟
Or does it have to do with our origin,
أو ان للأمر علاقة في أصولنا،
nationality
أو في جنسيتنا
or bank account?
أو في حسابنا المصرفي؟
This personal exercise turned out to be a discovery.
تبين هذا المجهود الشخصي لاحقا على أنه اكتشاف.
Suddenly I realized that Humanae was useful for many people.
وفجأة أدركت حينها ان "هيوماناي" مفيد جدا للعديد من الأشخاص.
It represents a sort of mirror
لأنه نوعا ما يمثل مرآة
for those who cannot find themselves reflected in any label.
للذين لا يستطيعون تصنيف انفسهم على اي شكل.
It was amazing
وكان ذلك مدهشا
that people started to share their thoughts about the work with me.
اذ بدأ الناس بمشاركة أفكارهم معي حول المشروع.
I have hundreds of that,
ولدي مئات منها،
I will share with you, too.
وسوف أطلعكم عليها ايضا.
A mother of 11 years --
واحدة منهم هي من أم لأحدى عشر سنة
A mother of an 11-year-old girl wrote me,
كتبت لي أم لطفلة في الحادية عشرة من العمر
"Very good for me as a tool to work on her confidence,
انها وبالنسبة لي أداة رائعة جدا للعمل على زيادة ثقة ابنتي بنفسها،
as this past weekend
اذ ان في نهاية الأسبوع الماضي
one of her girlfriends argued with her that she does not belong
تجادلت احدى صديقاتها معها عن عدم انتمائها أو ملاءمتها في المجتمع
and should not be allowed to live in Norway.
وانه يجب عدم السماح لها بالعيش في النرويج.
So your work has a very special place in my heart
لذا فان لعملك مكانة خاصة جدا في قلبي
and it's very important for me."
وهو أيضاً مهم جداً بالنسبة لي.
A woman shared her portrait on Facebook and wrote,
شاركت احدى النساء صورتها على فيسبوك وقامت بالتعليق عليها،
"All my life,
"طوال حياتي،
people from across the globe had difficulties to place me in a group,
واجه البشر من جميع أنحاء العالم صعوبات لتصنيفي في مجموعة،
a stereotype,
أو في صورة نمطية،
a box.
أو حتى في صندوق.
Perhaps we should stop.
ربما وجب علينا التوقف.
Instead of framing, ask the individual,
اذ عوضا عن محاولة تصنيف الشخص، قم بالاستفسار منه
'How would you label yourself?'
"كيف يمكنك تصنيف نفسك؟
Then I would say,
عندها سأقول،
'Hi. I'm Massiel.
'مرحبا. أنا ماسييل.
I'm a Dominican-Dutch,
أنا من أصول دومينيكية هولندية،
I grew up in a mixed family
نشأت في أسرة مختلطة
and I'm a bisexual woman.' "
وانا امرأة شاذة.
Besides these unexpected and touching reactions,
وإلى جانب هذه الردود الغير المتوقعة والمؤثرة،
Humanae finds a new life in a different variety of fields.
يجد "هيوماناي" حياة جديدة في مجموعات متنوعة من مختلف المجالات.
Just to show you some examples,
ولأظهر لكم بعض الأمثلة،
illustrators and art students
يستخدم الرسامون وطلاب الفن "هيوماناي"
using it as a reference for their sketches and their studies.
كمرجع لدراساتهم ورسوماتهم
It's a collection of faces.
انها مجموعة من الوجوه.
Researchers in the fields of anthropology,
الباحثون في مجالات علم الإنسان،
physics and neuroscience
الفيزياء وعلم الأعصاب
use Humanae with different scientific approaches
يستخدمون "هيوماناي" في المناهج العلمية المختلفة
related to human ethnicity,
والتي تتعلق بالعرق البشري،
optophysiology,
علم وظائف الأعضاء وعلم البصريات،
face recognition
وتمييز الوجوه
or Alzheimer's.
أو مرض الزهايمر.
One of the most important impacts of the project
واحدة من أهم آثار هذا المشروع
is that Humanae was chosen to be the cover of Foreign Affairs,
هو انه تم اختيار "هيوماناي" ليكون غطاء مجلة الشؤون الخارجية،
one of the most relevant political publications.
واحدة من المطبوعات السياسية الأكثر أهمية.
And talking about foreign affairs,
وبمناسبة حديثنا عن الشؤون الخارجية،
I found the perfect ambassadors for my project ...
عثرت على السفراء المثاليين لمشروعي
teachers.
وهم المعلمون.
They are the ones that use Humanae as a tool for educational purposes.
هم من يستخدمون "هيوماناي" كأداة للأغراض التعليمية.
Their passion encourages me to go back to drawing classes,
شغفهم شجعني لأعود إلى صفوف الرسم،
but this time as a teacher myself.
ولكن هذه المرة كمعلمة.
My students,
طلابي،
both adults and kids,
من البالغين والاطفال،
paint their self-portraits,
يرسمون صورهم الذاتية،
trying to discover their own unique color.
في محاولة لاكتشاف لون بشرتهم.
As a photographer,
وكمصوره فوتوغرافية،
I realize that I can be a channel for others to communicate.
أدركت حينها انه من الممكن لي ان اكون قناة ليتواصل من خلالها الآخرون.
As an individual,
وكفرد،
as Angélica,
وكانجيليكا،
every time I take a picture,
أشعر في كل مرة التقط فيها صورة،
I feel that I am sitting in front of a therapist.
بأنني أجلس أمام طبيب معالج.
All the frustration, fear and loneliness
اذ ان كل الإحباط والخوف والشعور بالوحدة
that I once felt ...
والذي كنت أشعر به
becomes love.
تحول الى حب.
The last country --
البلد الأخير
the last country in the world who abolished slavery
البلد الأخير والذي قام بإلغاء منهج العبودية في العالم
is the country where I was born,
هو البلد الذي ولدت فيه،
Brazil.
البرازيل.
We still have to work hard to abolish discrimination.
ما زال على جميعنا العمل وبجهد للقضاء على التمييز العنصري
That remains a common practice worldwide,
اذ انه لا يزال ممارسة شائعة في جميع أنحاء العالم،
and that will not disappear by itself.
ولن يختفي من تلقاء نفسه.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)